Inventory of the John Marshall Papers 1771-1959
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, Family Members and Other Individuals, 1771-1916, n.d. (Box 1-5)
  - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1771-1835, n.d., 269 items. (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1820-1829., 87 items. (Box 2-4)
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1826., 13 items. (Box-folder 3:4-5)
        - Timothy Pickering, Salem, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], 17 January 1826., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
          Thanks him for a copy of his [John Marshall's] history of the English colonies of North America which Joseph Story delivered a few weeks earlier; quotes Lord Kames [?] from his The Gentleman Farmer(1779); "I disregard the present rebellion of our Americans; for they will soon be reduced to obedience;" discusses present westward movement of the American population and predicts a new western confederacy of the movement of the national capital westward in the next generation; comments upon his [John Marshall's] statements on slavery, mentioning Colonel [Edward] Carrington's and Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson's views on miscegenation and the Colonization Society's efforts; discusses Georgia's Governor [George M.] Troup's detested views on the slaves and Creek Indians, which seem to be held by most Georgians, who would defy the authority of the Union if they dared; that authority rests on "the purity, the intellegence and the firmness" of the Supreme Court; hopes he [John Marshall] long remains at the head.
        - Timothy] Pickering, Salem, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], 24 January 1826., 7 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
          Has read Mr. [William Branch] Giles' latest article in the Richmond Enquirer on John Quincy Adams, which attributes his [John Quincy Adams's] "past conversion to Jeffersonism" to " his own personal promotion and aggrandizement;" Giles claims that Adams' message indicated his intentions to introduce unlimited powers into the government, but he [Timothy Pickering] disagrees; discusses Adams' policies regarding internal improvements, a national university, and the promotion of agriculture, all of which Washington recommended, and their constitutionality; discusses Giles, his character, and his political ambitions; writes of James Monroe's and William Pinckney's treaty with Great Britain and their letter to Congress, Monroe's bid for the Presidency, and his subsequent reconciliation with Jefferson; mentions Secretary of the State Robert Smith's correspondence with the British Minister [?] Jackson; his resignation, and published defense; discusses the death of Virginian U.S. District Court Judge Cyrus Griffin and the appointment of his successor John Tyler, ex-Governor of Virginia; which was made to make room for Monroe as Governor; Monroe was appointed to the State Department, "the vestibule to the President's Palace," when Smith resigned; discusses Jefferson's motives for not laying the treaty with Great Britain before Congress; concludes with Joseph Hopkinson's thoughts on Jefferson, Madison, and Monroe.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 5 February 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
          Left Alexandria for Washington a day early because the weather was good for traveling; he, [Bushrod] Washington, and [Gabriel] Duval await the arrival of their brother Justices [Joseph] Story and [Smith] Thompson; Judge Johnson went by way of Norfolk and will not arrive till Wednesday or Thursday; Judge [Thomas] Todd is unable to make the journey; discusses his journey and health: "I am under the persecution of the infuenza;" will open the court and wait on the President tomorrow.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.] to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, Richmond, Virginia], 12 February [18]26., 1 page. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
          Discusses his daily routine and his health; [Judge Joseph] Story arrived today; he was delayed a week in Philadelphia by influenza; discusses a loan of $200 to Tom [Thomas Marshall, his son]; has received three invitations for dinner parties this week; discusses the gaiety of the Washington social scene; jests about Lucy Fisher [his niece] marrying [Dr. Daniel Norborne Norton] and persuading him to run for Congress.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 12 March 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
          John [Marshall, his son] passed through the city, but he did not have a chance to see him; was pleased to hear that she was well, expecting "the uncommon warmth of the season had relaxed your system so as to distress your feelings;" he enjoys his usual health; "was at a very great crowd at Mrs. [John Quincy] Adams' drawing room;" dined yesterday with Mr. [John] Randolph [of Roanoke] who is as much engaged in party politics as he has always been.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to Timothy Pickering, [Salem, Massachusetts], 20 March 1826., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
          Congratulates him on his good health; gives his thoughts on Southern slavery; mentions Georgia's Governor [George M. Troup] and the treaty with the Creeks; discusses Mr. [William Branch] Giles; thanks him for his recollections of the events of the last twenty years.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Samuel Bayard, Princeton, New Jersey, 15 June 1826., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
          Has received his letter expressing his interest in the position of the clerk of the Supreme Court; the applicants are numerous and worthy; recalls their former acquaintance, and is confident in his competence, but wants to make such an important appointment "without any pre-engagements."
          Rush Rhees Library, University of Rochester, Rochester, New York.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Monroe, [n.p.], 30 July 1826., 2 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
          Replies to his letter recommending Mr. [?] Randall for the vacant office in the Clerkship of the Supreme Court; discusses his feelings regarding the appointment; has been having trouble with famine and drought.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Judge [?] Fay, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 15 September 1826., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
          Discusses marriage arrangements of his son Edward [Carrington Marshall] with the Judge's daughter.
        - J[ohn] M[arshall], Richmond, [Virginia], to [Judge Fay, Cambridge, Massachusetts], 15 October 1826., 4 pages. Draft of ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
          Apologizes for his last letter of 15 September 1826; did not realize that he [Fay] was opposed to Edward Carrington Marshall's marriage to his [Fay's] daughter; "I hope Edward has received notice of your decision... It will be [a] kindness to awaken him as soon as possible from the dreams of happiness in which he has been too long indulging."
        - Jos[eph] Hopkinson, Philad[elphia, Pennsylvania], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 27 October 1826., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
          Has finally discovered the letters in the Aurora from 23 October to 5 November 1795 written by the "Calm Observer" relating to the charge of illegal payment of the President's salary and the replies thereto by [Alexander] Hamilton and O.[?] Wolcott; these were not written by [William Branch] Giles; Judge [Bushrod] Washington had to break up his court because of ill-health.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [T. S. Hinde, Kentucky ?], 16 December [1826?]., 1 page. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
          Has received his letter by Mr. [?] Doddridge; apologizes for any inconvenience which may be caused by the disposal of the letters of recommendation which the recipient sent by Mr. [?] Rowan and Colonel [?] Johnson.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to "nephew" James Marshall, Winchester, [Virginia], 29 December 1826., 4 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
          Discusses legal principles involved in the Fairfax lands case.
          Including TCy of ALS. 4 pages.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to Timothy Pickering, Salem, Massachusetts, 15 March 1827., 2 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
        Has seen in the papers discussions between his brother Johnson [?] and him [Timothy Pickering] respecting Count Pulaske [Pulaski] and the Battle of Germantown; "with the exception of Judge [?] Peters, yourself, & Mr. [?] Wolcot[t] I can scarcely find any person who was conspicuous on the great theatre of our country when I first began to mix in public affairs;" asks if he will travel south to Washington; discusses George Washington and his firmness of character.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James K[eith] Marshall, Moreland near Oak Hill, Fauquier [County, Virginia], 3 July 1827., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
        Encloses a check on the bank of Winchester for $600 to be endorsed to Mr. [?] Smith; was surprised that the sale of the land was $200 less than he thought; Alexander Marshall informed him [John Marshall] that he settled $200 which he owed him with Mr. Smith; finished cutting his wheat and rye last week; his corn has suffered from the cold wet spring and now from drought; discusses weather and crop pests.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to H[enry] B[idleman] Bascom, [n.p.], 19 November 1827., 1 page. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
        Discusses the science of agriculture and whether or not it should be taught at a university.
      - Joseph Story, Salem, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 15 December 1827., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
        Has read the review which will be published in the forthcoming January 1828 edition of the North American Review of his [John Marshall's] History of the Colonies; encloses a copy of it; hopes to meet him in January and introduce Mrs. Story to him.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts], 30 December 1827., 3 pages. ALS. (Draft not sent?) (Box-folder 3:5)
        Has received his flattering letter and biography of him and warmly expresses his gratitude; accommodations for Mrs. Story may be had at Mr. [?] Rapine's in Washington; discusses the present contest for the Presidency; fears that "our constitution is not to be so long lived as its real friends have hoped."
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1828., 16 items. (Box-folder 3:5-6)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, [n.p.], to John Randolph, [n.p.], 6 March 1828., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
          Thanks him for a copy of his speech on "retrenchment and reform;" intended to call on him, but the pressure of official duties and the indolence of age have prevented it.
        - J[ohn] R[andolph] of Roanoke to John Marshall, [n.p.], 20 March 1828., 2 pages. AL. (Box-folder 3:5)
          Must decline his invitation to be his companion on the Potomac because of his ill health; Mr. [?] Sheppherd has given a good account of "our Jacobin Banker's Clerk" [?]; discusses Sheppherd's and the clerk's lives.
        - J[ohn] M[arshall], Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 26 March 1828., 2 pages. Cy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
          Begs him to accept his portrait painted by Mr. [Chester] Harding in Washington as a token of his sincere and affectionate friendship; will not send it to Richmond until Mr. [Horatio] Greenough casts his bust; enjoyed a pleasant trip from Washington to Richmond where he has seen none but his family since his return; the spirit of party is extremely bitter, but he plans to leave for the upper country; had one of his [Joseph Story's] fish yesterday; received news from Mr. [?] McGruder of the loss of his [John Marshall's] sortout.
        - H[enry] Clay, Washington, [D.C.], to J[ohn] Marshall, n.p., 8 April 1828., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
          Takes the liberty to write him; regrets that it was necessary for him [John Marshall] to announce publicly his feelings on the election, because it will not subject him to the abuse of the partisans.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 1 May 1828., 4 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
          Did not have a chance to answer Mr. [Chester] Harding's letter asking what should be done with his [John Marshall's] portrait; if he [Chester Harding] is in Boston, have him deliver it to you [Joseph Story]; asks him [Joseph Story] to take care of it till he [John Marshall] can have it and his bust sent to Richmond; discusses how the Marylander misquoted him on the coming election; an epidemic has prevailed extensively in Richmond.
        - John Randolph of Roanoke to John Marshall, [n.p.], 6 March 1828., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
          Has received his letter and is grateful for his kind words; although the still burnt Kentucky Whiskey is nauseous to my palate, "I can yet enjoy the aroma of an exquisite glass of Madeira, or Paxasete, or Burgundy and I doubt whether my head would have been more affected by a bottle of Clos Von gedt, capped with another of such [silvery?] Champagne, than by your truly kind note."
        - [John Marshall, n.p.] to [?], 29 May 1828., 2 pages. ALS. Incomplete. (Box-folder 3:6)
          Discusses the recipient's proposed amendment to a bill before the House of Representatives concerning the U.S. Circuit Court System.
        - John Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Willis Cowlin, James Sezer, and James Gray, [Richmond, Virginia], 28 June 1828., 1 page. Ph of L. (Box-folder 3:6)
          Letter declining their honor of joining the Richmond and Manchester Sabbath School in a 4th of July procession, not because he does not believe in the principles inspiring it, but because he must leave town due to Mrs. Marshall's feeble health; (the letter was probably written and signed by a secretary).
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to William B. Sprague, West Springfield, Massachusetts, 22 July 1828., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
          Cannot satisfy his request to send him letters with autographs of the Virginian signers of the Declaration of Independence as they have not been preserved or contain private communications; has read and enjoyed the sermons he sent; discusses the nature of church and state in post-Revolutionary Virginia; gratified by his [William B. Sprague's] sermon on intemperance and gives his [John Marshall's] views on the subject.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, [Richmond, Virginia?] to his son [Thomas Marshall?, "Oak Hill," Fauquier County, Virginia?], 29 August 1828., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. Signature torn. (Box-folder 3:6)
          Discusses a land case concerning Mrs. [?] Clarke and Mr. [?] Swan, and Mr. [?] Pollard; have no further communications with Swan as "he has no idea of...frank dealing"; Mr. [?] Fiske wrote that he can lend money for Mrs. [?] Carrington; please send down his [John Marshall's] ponies with Charles Smith or Mr. [?] Colston.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Martin P. Marshall, Flemingsburg, Fleming County, Kentucky, 2 September 1828., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
          Has just received Mr. [?] Triplett's letter and is willing to allow him 20% commission on the money he may collect from the estate of Mr. [?] Davies [?]; discusses arrangements for drawing money on his [John Marshall's] account; asks him to pay costs incurred in the execution of the above matter; discusses election of General [Andrew] Jackson.
          William L. Clements Library, Ann Arbor, Michigan.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to son [Thomas Marshall?, Oak Hill, Fauquier County, Virginia?], l2[?] September 1828., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
          Makes arrangements to pay [ ] $1000 to Swan for a land purchase.
          University of Virginia?
        - Thomas Marshall, Oak Hill, [Faquier County, Virginia], to John Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], 26 September 1828., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
          Has received his letter concerning news of the birth of Margaret's [(Lewis) Marshall]'s nephew; mentions health of his family, including the children's whooping cough; prices in the Alex[andri]a flour market and how the dry weather is affecting crops; writes of his own agricultural efforts, including the operation of a large roller for his corn fields; has been unable to send down the horses; will attend a sale at Westover on Mr. [?] Lewis's request; Mr. Lewis, Mr. [?] Coiston, and Mr. Cha[rle]s B. Smith are not able to take the horses to him [John Marshall] or to Aunt [?] Carrington.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 29 October 1828., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
          Has finished reading his centennial discourse on the first settlement of Salem; was touched by his portrayal of the story of the Indians; especially enjoyed the passages respecting the Lady Arabella Johnson; read with interest his sketch of the recently deceased [Robert] Trimble, brother Supreme Court Justice; congratulates him on the appointment of [Joseph] Hopkinson[to the Eastern District of Pennsylvania District Court Judgeship].
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Norfolk, [Virginia], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, [Virginia], 31 October l82[8?]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
          The case will not be finished till Saturday and he [John Marshall] will not be home till Tuesday; had a pleasant sail down the river to Norfolk; boards in a very agreeable house.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], to "Mr. Librarian" [?, Washington, D.C.], [c. 1828]., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
          Requests him to purchase two more copies of [Joseph] Story's three volume [ Public and General Statutes passed by the Congress of the United States, 1789-1827] for the Supreme Court.
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1829., 10 items. (Box-folder 4:1)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 1 February 1829., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:1)
          The sick [Supreme Court] judges have arrived; he continues his morning walks; they dined with the President and Mrs. [John Quincy] Adams on Friday; discusses their feelings on [Andrew] Jackson's election; Jackson is expected in the city in a fortnight; mentions Mrs. Jackson's death; discusses his [John Marshall's] dinner invitations; tell Mr. [?] Call [Cole?] the secretaries are sick, and [Henry] Clay caught a cold by attending the colonization society; discusses the upcoming inauguration.
          Including Pst of ALS. 2 pages. Also including TCy of ALS. 1 page.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, Richmond, Virginia], 19 February 1829., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:1)
          Encloses a letter to be sent to Mr. [?] Payne; imagines that Oby has carried out the clover seed from the cellar; received news from his son James [Keith Marshall] that she was not well; has written to his son in a feeble attempt to console him [Thomas Marshall on the death of his wife Margaret]; receive news from Jaquelin [Marshall] of his new son, Jaquelin Jr.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Wilis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 28 February 1829., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:1)
          Has had no news of her and is worried; discusses her delicate health; received news from his son Edward [Carrington Marshall] who grieves for his brother's [Thomas's] loss; received a serious and very religious letter from Thomas, who is much occupied with his children and superintends his son John's education.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to Thomas Marshall, Oak Hill, Fauquier County, Virginia, 20 March 1829., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:1)
          Answers his letter of 21 February; is pleased that he has turned to religion and reason in handling his grief in losing his wife; is glad that he has kept John at hand [instead of sending him to Princeton]; an epidemic has hit the University [of Virginia] at Charlottesville, and a son of General [?] Jones is dying of the fever; this city [Washington] is full of office-sickness; discusses the spoils system.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 11 June 1829., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:1)
          Has received his letter enclosing a copy of Judge [Joseph] Hopkinson's commission; will attend Virginia's constitutional convention as a delegate; explains his feelings regarding his election to the convention and to its being convened.
        - 3 July 1829. J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:1)
          Has received his letter accompanying his anniversary address to the Suffolk bar and Mr. [John] Brazer's discourse at the interment of Dr. [Edward] Holyoke; advises him against precipitous fulfillment of the publication requirements for his Dane Professorship [at Harvard]; his attention has been turned to the two great cases before the Supreme Court; place your thoughts of them on paper; Mr. [Smith] Thompson will look into the New York case; discusses the matters which will come before the Virginia constitutional, convention: property qualifications, senate apportioning, basis of representation, freehold suffrage.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, [Richmond, Virginia], to Mr. Rawlings, [Richmond, Virginia], 25 July 1829., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:1)
          After much hesitation, he must complain to him about his barking dog which has distressed his [John Marshall's] wife who is in very poor health; is extremely apologetic over causing any inconvenience.
          Including Pst of ALS. 1 page. (Incomplete).
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 30 September 1829., 2 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:1)
          Has read his discourses pronounced as Dane Professor of Law at Harvard; is impressed with his teaching efforts: "Our southern youths would stumble at the threshhold [of your most appalling course].. .You yankees have more perseverence"; no hopes that he lives to read his lectures; still regrets being a member of Virginia's constitutional convention.
        - M[artin] Van Buren, [Washington, D.C.], to John Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], 11 November [l8]29., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 4:1)
          Will be unable to accept his invitation as he is leaving town on Saturday and will be busy until then.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [?, Richmond, Virginia], 21 December 1829., 2 pages. ALS. Draft, not sent? (Box-folder 4:1)
          Accepts his election as [Bushrod] Washington's successor' in some honorary position [President of the American Colonization Society?].
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1830-1839., 55 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1830., 12 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
        - [John Marshall, Washington, D.C.?] to [John C. Calhoun?, Washington, D.C.?], 11 January 1830., 2 pages. AL. Incomplete draft, unsigned. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Has finished reading his 1809 Fourth of July oration and his December 1828 speech "on the constitutionality of the Tariff and the true nature of state government;" his speech in the Senate was well-argued: "Is it possible that South Carolina can withstand so powerful an appeal to... her patriotism.. .and her real interest?"; is flattered by the notice he took of the author of the Life of Washington [John Marshall] in his notes.